<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Margery good-covv, that gave a gallon of milk, and kickt down the pail, and beraid the milk-maid, what did she merit? speak, gentlemen. Or, A short discourse, shewing that there is not a farthing due from this nation to old Oliver for all his pretended services: and if any thing be given his son, it must be in respect to his own personal virtues, and modest behaviours, during his being Protector; and not out of any respect to his ill-deserving father.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89525</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863050</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115232</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240955685</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M590</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E984_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202924</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863050</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99863050e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89525)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115232)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 146:E984[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Margery good-covv, that gave a gallon of milk, and kickt down the pail, and beraid the milk-maid, what did she merit? speak, gentlemen. Or, A short discourse, shewing that there is not a farthing due from this nation to old Oliver for all his pretended services: and if any thing be given his son, it must be in respect to his own personal virtues, and modest behaviours, during his being Protector; and not out of any respect to his ill-deserving father.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 30th"; May 30".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Cromwell, Richard, 1626-1712.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115232:1"/>
            <p>Margery Good-Covv, That gave a Gallon of Milk, and kickt down the Pail, and beraid the Milk-Maid, what did she merit? speak, Gentlemen.</p>
            <p>Or, A Short DISCOURSE, Shewing That there is not a Farthing due from this Nation to old <hi>Oliver</hi> for all his pretended services: and if any thing be given his Son, it must be in respect to his own personal Virtues, and modest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviours, during his being Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector; and not out of any respect to his ill-deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115232:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115232:2"/>
            <head>Margery Good-Cow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Officers of the Army propound (but it is admirable with what face they can do it) that so much and so much should be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the late Protector and his Mother, because of the deserts of old <hi>Oliver.</hi> Certainly the Gentlemen are in jest, or else they partake highly with the said <hi>Oliver,</hi> his bad intentions, and therefore judge him meritorious lest they should condemn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. What has he deserved, that pul'd down the King, and enthron'd himself, and ruled over the people with a rod of iron? His late ambitions o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-plainly shew the hypocrisie of his first actings. And the Parliament had more need to save the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney propounded by the Officers, to pay the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldiers, and other great Debts the Nation is engaged in, by the wild ambitions of the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, then needlesly to throw the same away up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on those that have enough of their own to live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably and comfortably upon.</p>
            <p>Yet if the Parliament shall in their wisedome think fit to give some honourable Pension to the Son (and Mother for his sake) I hope it shall be as a reward of his own Virtues, his modesty, true se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity, gentle and manly deportment; and not as a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115232:3"/>sacrifice to the Insolence, Turbulence, and Boyste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous usurpations, and <hi>Jehu</hi>-like proceedings of his Father. To reward the Virtues of the Son, may be of good use to posterity; but to palliate the Vices and Enormities of the Father, will be perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and an encouragement to the next person that shall have the ambition and opportunity, to in vade the Commonwealth, and <hi>Caesar</hi>-like to crow over his Masters.</p>
            <p>Yet the truth of it is, since the Parliament, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the wounted Policy of all Common-wealths, did continue one man so long General, and thereby thrust him into temptations which he was not able to bear, he is the more excusable as to his memory, and they the less to be pityed for their interruption. And it is to be hoped they will never again continue any one man long in the command of the Army, unless they intend he shall command them out of doors, as their <hi>Caesar</hi> did.</p>
            <p>And if they shall be tempted (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) for the continuance of their own Session, to comply with the chief Sword-man, to perpetuate him in his Command, upon condition he shall continue them for ever sitting; it were to be wished they would please to remember, how ill such Policy has formerly succeeded.</p>
            <p>And now being loath to harp any longer upon these not so tunable strings, I shall observe to the Reader the happiness of a Commonwealth, even in this one instance of the liberty of Printing; that our mouths are open. For it suits not with the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115232:3"/>Interest not with the Magnanimity of a true Commonwealth to stop the Press. This is a thing for the petty and pedling way of Princes, that are afraid of every thing, and whose ravenous Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by's must screw money out of the Weekly Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and all mouths must be stopped save only one or two that shall play the Sycophants so far, as to nauseate every ingenous Reader. And let me tell you, Country-men, That when ever you see a restriction upon the Press, then know that your hoped for Commonwealth is taking its leave, and base selfish designs and interests are getting head again. The liberty of Printing, as it satisfies the impulse of the spirit of those that write, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents the Reader, and puts him in hopes and thoughts that we are free men, because our mouths are not stopped: so it may (if they please) give great light to the Parliament all along; yea, greater light then any they can receive from those who speak only pleasing things for their own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, to get into places of trust and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And indeed ever since the Abolition of Kingship, the Nation has enjoyed divers effects of freedom. Mens wits have budded forth with new Inventions in all Arts and Sciences, even to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Whereas in the times of the Kings, mens souls were made like Mill-horses to go round in a certain path of book-knowledge, which the Bishops and their Confederates in the Universities had tracked out under the name of Orthodoxism, not only in Religion, but in all other knowledge; which tended to benum and stupifie the Wits of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115232:4"/>and to hinder them from seeking into any thing farther, or getting more light; that so they might not discover the works of darkness of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surping Prince and Parasitical Prelates. Since the removal of Kingship and Episcopacy, the wits of this Nation have been rouzed as it were out of a Lethargy: which may be seen in a world of new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions communicated by the Press, and a world of accommodations in the Commonwealth, which mens wits set at liberty have found out for their own profit, and mutual accommodation one of another. And indeed, my soul was tormented within me to see the Nation returning under the late Protector, to blockishness &amp; brutish adoration of men, and forms, and methods, and to be ready to receive the paltrie, but princely shackles of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxism in all kinds of knowledge, to fetter and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slave their wits, and to put a <hi>non-plus ultra</hi> to all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Inventions. But I hope the great God of light, and all useful liberty, has once again broken the Bands of darkness that were in fastening about the Understandings of the people of this Nation; and that he will cause Light so to increase, that all the lovers of deeds of darkness may be ashamed, and either repent, or at least finde no opportunity to shroud their ugly self-seeking practices from the eyes of the people of this Commonwealth; but that they will be forced to turn honest in despight of their great noses, or any other sumptoms of the Fox, for fear of being uncas'd in their Craft: and that after they have been honest a while perforce,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115232:4"/>they will find so much sweetness, honour, comfort of Conscience, quietness of spirit, health of Bones, and length of life attending upon the waies of honesty, which is the only true wisdom (and the rest falsly called wisdome, but jugling knavery, and stinking fox-like shuffling) that they will blesse God for that juncture of affairs which brought them into such a condition, (which is an heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth) and ever after abhor all Legerdemain, and profess and practise that sincerity, which only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a true man.</p>
            <p>And for their encouragement, let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that if the old Protector had not been so much a Fox, he might in all probability have lived now a Man in great favour and power, and General of the Armies of the Commonwealth of <hi>England;</hi> whereas craftily, but not wisely, catching at a sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and enamoured of those baubles he some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times scorned, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Mace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) he lost his peace, tranquillity, health, comfort, applause of his own Conscience, of God and Angels, and sincere men, to find the empty blandishments of servile Parasites, vaine pageantry, trouble of mind, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death in great disquiet of soul and spirit.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>